<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>

<section xml:id="section-53">
			<title>Volumes by Cylindrical Shells</title>
			
				<objectives>
					<ul>
						<li>
							Determine whether the Shell Method, Disk Method, or Washer Method is most appropriate to compute the volume of a solid of revolution, and compute the volume by integrating with respect to <m>x</m> or <m>y</m>
						</li>
						
					</ul>
				</objectives>
			<subsection xml:id="section-53-beforeclass">
				<title>Before Class</title>
				
				<figure>
					<caption>Pre-Class Video 1</caption>
					<url href = "https://mymedia.ou.edu/media/5.3-1/0_weag3qcy"/>
				</figure>
				<figure>
					<caption>Pre-Class Video 2</caption>
					<url href = "https://mymedia.ou.edu/media/5.3-2/0_mx0xmcp9"/>
				</figure>
				<figure>
					<caption>Pre-Class Video 3</caption>
					<url href = "https://mymedia.ou.edu/media/5.3-3/0_og9j6r23"/>
				</figure>
				
				<subsubsection xml:id="section-53-slicing-cylinders">
					<title>Slicing with Cylinders</title>
					<example>
						<statement>
							Let <m>f(x) = x-x^2</m>.
							<ol label="a">
								<li>
									Sketch the region bounded by <m>f(x)</m> and the <m>x-</m>axis.
								</li>
								<li>
									Set up (but do not solve) an integral to find the volume of the solid created by rotating the region about the line <m>y = 0</m>.  Why can we use the disk method?
								</li>
								<li>
									Are there problems if we instead rotate about the line <m>x = 0</m>?  Explain with pictures, words, etc.
								</li>
							</ol>
						</statement>
					</example>
					
					<example>
						<statement>
							Again consider <m>f(x) = x-x^2</m>.
							<ol label="a">
								<li>
									Draw four midpoint rectangles for the area of the region bounded by <m>f(x)</m> and the <m>x-</m>axis.  Be sure to label things appropriately!
								</li>
									
								<li>
									Sketch what happens to the rectangles when rotated about the line <m>x = 0</m>.
								</li>
									
								<li>
									How can we find the surface area of the shape from part (b)?  
								</li>
									
								<li>
									Use your answers from parts (b) and (c) to approximate the volume of the solid.
								</li>
									
								<li>
									Write an expression that uses <q>infinitely many</q> rectangles to approximate the the volume of the solid.
								</li>
									
								<li>
									Convert your answer from part (d) into an integral expression, and evaluate it.
								</li>
							</ol>
						</statement>
					</example>
				</subsubsection>
				<subsubsection xml:id="section-53-shell-method">
					<title>The Shell Method</title>
					
					<assemblage>
						<title>Method of Cylindrical Shells</title>
						<p>
							Let <m>f(x)</m> be a continuous function on the interval <m>[a,b]</m>.  Then, the volume of the solid created by rotating the region bounded by <m>f(x)</m> and the <m>x-</m>axis about the line <m>x = 0</m> is given by
							<me>
								\int_a^b 2\pi r(x)f(x)\, dx
							</me>
							where <m>r(x)</m> is the radius function.
						</p>
					</assemblage>
					
					<example>
						<statement>
							Consider the region bounded by the curve <m>y = 2\sqrt{x}</m>, the <m>x-</m>axis, and the line <m>x = 4</m>.  
							<ol label="a">
								<li>
									Sketch and label the region.
								</li>
									
								<li>
									Sketch and label a typical approximating cylinder, when rotated about <m>x = 0</m>.
								</li>
									
								<li>
									Use the formula for the cylinder to set up an integral for the volume of the resulting solid, then evaluate it.
								</li>
							</ol>
						</statement>
					</example>
				</subsubsection>
			</subsection>
			<subsection xml:id="section-53-preclass">
				<title>Pre-Class Activities</title>
				
				<example><statement>
					If you were presented with a problem, how would you know whether to use the disk method, washer method, or shell method?  Examples 1 and 2 might be good places to get ideas.
				</statement></example>
					 
					
				<example><statement>
					Find the volume of the solid obtained by rotating the region bouded by <m>y = 2x^2 - x^3</m> and <m>y = 0</m> about the <m>y-</m>axis.
				</statement></example>
				
			</subsection>
			<subsection xml:id="section-53-inclass">
				<title>In Class</title>
				
				<example><statement>
					Use the shell method to find the volume of the solid generated by revolving the region bounded by the curves <m>xy = 1</m>, <m>x = 0</m>, <m>y = 1</m>, and <m>y = 3</m> about the <m>x-</m>axis.  Hint: Sketch the solid and its approximating cylinders.
				</statement></example>					
					
				<example><statement>
					Find the volume of the solid created by rotating the region bounded by the curves <m>y = x^3</m>, <m>y = 0</m>, <m>x = 1</m>, and <m>x = 2</m> about the <m>y-</m>axis.  Be sure to label your diagram, if you choose to draw one.
				</statement></example>

				<example><statement>
					Find the volume of the solid created by rotating the first-quadrant region bounded by the curves <m>y = 4x-x^2</m>, and <m>y = x</m> about the <m>y-</m>axis.  Be sure to label your diagram, if you choose to draw one.
				</statement></example>
	
				<example><statement>
					Find the volume of the solid created by rotating the region bounded by the curves <m>x = 2y^2</m>, <m>y\geq 0</m>, and <m>x=8</m> about <m>y = 2</m>.  Hint: Draw and label a diagram.  Remember that this is a function of <m>y</m>, not a function of <m>x</m>!
				</statement></example>
	
				<example><statement>
					Find the volume of the solid created by rotating the region bounded by the curves <m>y = x^3</m>, <m>y = 8</m>, <m>x = 0</m> about <m>x = 2</m>.  Be sure to label your diagram, if you choose to draw one.
				</statement></example>
			  
			</subsection>
			
			<subsection xml:id="section-53-afterclass">
				<title>After Class Activities</title>
				
				<example><statement>
					Consider the region between the curve <m>y = \sqrt{x}</m>, <m>y = 0</m>, and <m>x = 1</m>.
					<ol label="a">
						<li>
							Sketch the region.  Label all important information.
						</li>
						<li>
							Sketch a typical approximating cylinder for the volume formed when the region is rotated about the <m>x-</m>axis.
						</li>
					</ol>
				</statement></example>
				
				<example><statement>
					Find the volume of the solid created by rotating the region bounded by the curves <m>x = 2y^2</m>, <m>x = y^2 + 1</m> about <m>y = -2</m>.
				</statement></example>
					
				<example><statement>
					Sketch the region described in the volume integral below:
						<me>V = \int_1^4 \dfrac{2\pi (y+2)}{y^2}\, dy</me>
				</statement></example>
					 
					
				<example><statement>
					The region bounded by the curves <m>y = -x^2 + 6x-8</m> and <m>y = 0</m> is rotated about the <m>y-</m>axis.
						<ol label="a">
							<li>
								Sketch the region described above.
							</li>
								
							<li>
								Of our three methods, which one do you want to use?  Give a quick explanation why you chose that particular method.
							</li>
								
							<li>
								Compute the volume of the solid.
							</li>	 
						</ol>
				</statement></example>
					
				<example><statement>	
					Consider the region bounded by the curves <m>y = 4x</m>, <m>y = 0</m>, and <m>x = 2</m>.  Find the volume of the solid formed when the region is rotated about the given lines:
					<ol label="a">
						<li>
							The <m>y-</m>axis
						</li>						 
							
						<li>
							<m>x = 4</m>
						</li>
						
					</ol>
				</statement></example>
			</subsection>
		</section>
		